Register of the Charles Easton Rothwell papers, 1924-1995
Hoover Institution Archives
- Correspondence, 1933-1982 (Box 4-9)
  - Rothwell, Francis E., 1946 (Box-folder 9: 6)
  - Roucek, Joseph S., 1949 (Box-folder 9: 7)
  - Rowe, Thomas A., 1965 (Box-folder 9: 8)
    Includes Rowe's letter to President Harry S. Truman.
  - Royon, Betty, 1965-1967 (Box-folder 9: 9)
  - Rusk, Dean, 1949-1976 (Box-folder 9: 10)
  - Russell, Henry Potter, Mrs., 1966 (Box-folder 9: 11)
  - Russell, Madeleine H., 1964 (Box-folder 9: 12)
  - Salisbury, Winnifred, 1964 (Box-folder 9: 13)
  - San Francisco Public Library, 1965 (Box-folder 9: 14)
  - Santschi, Amanda H., 1965 (Box-folder 9: 15)
  - Saunders, Christopher, 1967 (Box-folder 9: 16)
  - Sayre, E. B., 1948 (Box-folder 9: 17)
  - Schmelzle, William K., 1949 (Box-folder 9: 18)
  - Sharp, Stanley, L., Mr. and Mrs., 1965 (Box-folder 9: 19)
  - Sharpe, Russell T., 1966-1967 (Box-folder 9: 20)
  - Sherman, Leslie, Mrs., 1966 (Box-folder 9: 21)
  - Shields, Deryl B., Mrs., 1962 (Box-folder 9: 22)
  - Shotwell, James T., 1948-1949 (Box-folder 9: 23)
  - Shulman, Irving, 1965 (Box-folder 9: 24)
  - Simpson, John L., 1962-1964 (Box-folder 9: 25)
  - Sims, Eugene P., Mrs., 1964 (Box-folder 9: 26)
  - Sisson, Edward O., Mrs., 1963 (Box-folder 9: 27)
  - Smith, C. R., 1966 (Box-folder 9: 28)
  - Smith, Margaret Chase, 1964 (Box-folder 9: 29)
  - Snavely, Guy E., 1955 (Box-folder 9: 30)
  - Staley, Eugene, 1949 (Box-folder 9: 31)
  - Stein, Jay W., 1949-1967 (Box-folder 9: 32)
  - Sterling, J. E. Wallace, 1951-1975 (Box-folder 9: 33)
  - Stettinius, Edward R., Jr., 1947-1949 (Box-folder 9: 34)
    See also: United Nations and State Department series.
  - Stevens, Danvers, 1966 (Box-folder 9: 35)
  - Stevens, Stoddard M., 1963-1964 (Box-folder 9: 36)
  - Stevenson, Adlai, 1952 (Box-folder 9: 37)
  - Stewart, Robert B., 1949 (Box-folder 9: 38)
  - Stewart, Samuel B., 1973 (Box-folder 9: 39)
  - Stix, Louis, 1965 (Box-folder 9: 40)
  - Suetens, N., 1951 (Box-folder 9: 41)
  - Sullivan, Carmel, 1949 (Box-folder 9: 42)
  - Sullivan, John L., 1949 (Box-folder 9: 43)
  - Summerskill, John, 1966 (Box-folder 9: 44)
  - Sutro, John A., 1949 (Box-folder 9: 45)
  - Swain?, Juanita, E., 1951 (Box-folder 9: 46)
  - Swayzee, Cleon O., 1966-1967 (Box-folder 9: 47)
  - Sweetser, Arthur, 1952 (Box-folder 9: 48)
  - Tam, Rosalie, 1966 (Box-folder 9: 49)
  - Tanaka, Hisako?, 1953 (Box-folder 9: 50)
  - Taylor, John, Mr. and Mrs., 1967 (Box-folder 9: 51)
  - Teller, Edward, 1964 (Box-folder 9: 52)
  - Thelen, Max, Jr., 1981 (Box-folder 9: 53)
  - Thompson, John M., 1966 (Box-folder 9: 54)
  - Thompson, Kenneth W., 1967 (Box-folder 9: 55)
  - Thorne, Harold W., Jr., Mrs., 1966 (Box-folder 9: 56)
  - Tice, Fred A., 1967 (Box-folder 9: 57)
  - Tickton, Sidney G., 1965 (Box-folder 9: 58)
  - Treat, Sidney W., 1965-1967 (Box-folder 9: 59)
  - Trefethen, E. E., Jr., 1967-1968 (Box-folder 9: 60)
  - Tucker, E. Louise, 1949 (Box-folder 9: 61)
  - Turtledove, Harry L., 1948-1949 (Box-folder 9: 62)
  - Tweedy, Mary Johnson, 1963-1967 (Box-folder 9: 63)
  - Underhill, Kirk, 1960 (Box-folder 9: 64)
  - University of California, Berkeley, 1967 (Box-folder 9: 65)
  - University of California. Los Angeles, 1966 (Box-folder 9: 66)
  - Valjavec, Fritz, 1951 (Box-folder 9: 67)
  - Van der Hart, Alexander, 1967 (Box-folder 9: 68)
  - Vaughn, R. Delong, 1955 (Box-folder 9: 69)
  - Verde Valley School, 1947-1949 (Box-folder 9: 70)
  - Vial, Jane, 1949 (Box-folder 9: 71)
  - Wagenen, Richard Van, 1949-1951 (Box-folder 9: 72)
  - Walker, E. H., 1949 (Box-folder 9: 73)
  - Walker, Robert J., 1966 (Box-folder 9: 74)
  - Wallace, L. F., 1949 (Box-folder 9: 75)
    Includes a letter to Mrs. Stettinius.
  - Wallace, Schuyler C., 1966 (Box-folder 9: 76)
  - Ward, Stuart, 1947 (Box-folder 9: 77)
  - Wax, Mel, 1967 (Box-folder 9: 78)
  - Webb, James E., 1967 (Box-folder 9: 79)
  - Weintraub, Ruth G., 1974 (Box-folder 9: 80)
  - Wellman, Harry R., 1967 (Box-folder 9: 81)
  - Wells, Robert, Mrs., 1967 (Box-folder 9: 82)
  - Wentworth, William P., 1966 (Box-folder 9: 83)
  - Whisler, George, 1955 (Box-folder 9: 84)
  - White, Byron R., 1965 (Box-folder 9: 85)
  - Wilderman, Sam, Mr. and Mrs., 1949 (Box-folder 9: 86)
  - William, Mary, 1967 (Box-folder 9: 87)
  - Williams, Franklin H., 1978 (Box-folder 9: 88)
  - Williams, Haydn, 1976 (Box-folder 9: 89)
  - Wilson, Elmo C., 1949 (Box-folder 9: 90)
  - Wilson, Howard E., 1948 (Box-folder 9: 91)
  - Wilson, Leslie Muir, 1939-1940 (Box-folder 9: 92)
  - Wilson, Louise, 1949 (Box-folder 9: 93)
  - Wolfe, Gregory Baker, 1974 (Box-folder 9: 94)
  - Wooten, Flaud, 1949 (Box-folder 9: 95)
  - Wormald, F. L., 1965-1967 (Box-folder 9: 96)
  - Wrenn, C. Gilbert, 1966-1967 (Box-folder 9: 97)
  - Wright, Evaline, 1965 (Box-folder 9: 98)
  - Wright, M. A., 1966 (Box-folder 9: 99)
  - Wriston, Henry H., 1958 (Box-folder 9: 100)
- Speeches and Writings, 1939-1983 (Box 10-21)
  Scope and Contents Note
  Articles, notes, oral history, outlines, remarks, speeches, statements and related correspondence, memoranda, and telegrams, arranged chronologically by title.
  - General
    - Articles, holograph (Box-folder 10: 1-2)
    - Invitations to speak
      - Accepted
        - 1947
          - February-July (Box-folder 10: 3)
          - September-December (Box-folder 10: 4)
        - 1948
          - January-April (Box-folder 10: 5)
          - May-June (Box-folder 10: 6)
          - July-December (Box-folder 10: 7)
        - 1949 (Box-folder 10: 8)
        - 1951 (Box-folder 10: 9)
        - 1952 (Box-folder 10: 10)
        - 1954 (Box-folder 10: 11)
        - 1955 (Box-folder 10: 12)
        - 1956 (Box-folder 10: 13)
        - 1957 (Box-folder 10: 14)
        - 1958 (Box-folder 10: 15)
        - 1960 (Box-folder 11: 1)
        - 1961 (Box-folder 11: 2)
        - 1966 (Box-folder 11: 3)
        - 1967 (Box-folder 11: 4)
        - 1971 (Box-folder 11: 5)
        - 1973 (Box-folder 11: 6)
      - Declined
        - 1947 (Box-folder 11: 7)
        - 1948 (Box-folder 11: 8)
        - 1955 (Box-folder 11: 9)
        - 1956-1957 (Box-folder 11: 10)
        - 1958 (Box-folder 11: 11)
    - Manuscript, typescript (Box-folder 11: 12)
    - Outline, typescript (Box-folder 11: 13-14)
    - Remarks, group discussion, typescript (Box-folder 11: 15)
    - Statement, third anniversary of the signing of the U.N. Charter, typescript (Box-folder 11: 16)
    - Miscellany (Box-folder 11: 17)
  - "A Critical Estimate of Tacitus as an Historian," typescript outline, undated (Box-folder 11: 18)
  - "A Spring Thing," a skit, typescript, undated (Box-folder 11: 19)
  - "American Foreign Policy Toward Europe," holograph outline, undated (Box-folder 11: 20)
  - "An Appraisal of Kulturgeschichte," typescript outline, undated (Box-folder 12: 1)
  - Article, Mills College Alumnae Weekly, typescript, undated (Box-folder 12: 2)
  - "Berlin Crisis and the U.N.," typescript, undated (Box-folder 12: 3)
  - "Challenges of Social Change to U.S.," holograph outline, undated (Box-folder 12: 4)
  - "Changing Great Power Relations in the Pacific Region," proposed study, typescript, undated (Box-folder 12: 5)
  - Commencement speech?, typescript, undated (Box-folder 12: 6)
  - "Commencement 1966," speech, typescript, undated (Box-folder 12: 7)
  - "Cooperation Outside the United Nations," Chapter IX, typescript, undated (Box-folder 12: 8)
  - "Cooperation within the ITO and the GATT," Chapter VII, typescript, undated (Box-folder 12: 9)
  - "Cooperation within the United Nations System," Chapter VIII, typescript, undated (Box-folder 12: 10)
  - "Development and Significance of International Health Organization, 1920-1950," Chapters I-VI, typescript, undated (Box-folder 12: 11)
  - "Development of the Council of Europe," typescript outline for a speech, undated (Box-folder 12: 12)
  - "Disarmament and Control of Atomic Energy," Chapters I-II and IV-V, typescript, undated (Box-folder 12: 13)
  - "Does the Government Make Up Its Mind?,", undated (Box-folder 12: 14)
    Includes typescript outline for a speech by Charles Rothwell and correspondence and draft of the minutes of a meeting by B. G. Chynoweth.
  - "Education and the World Scene," typescript outline, undated (Box-folder 12: 15)
  - "Education, Citizenship and Peace," holograph outline, undated (Box-folder 12: 16)
  - "Education for the Year 2000," typescript, undated (Box-folder 12: 17)
  - "Education, Foreign Policy, and International Relations," typescript manuscript, undated (Box-folder 12: 18)
  - Endowment speech, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, holograph outline, undated (Box-folder 12: 19)
  - "Europe: Battleground or Bulwark," typescript outline, undated (Box-folder 12: 20)
  - "European Factors Affecting American Foreign Policy," typescript, undated (Box-folder 12: 21)
  - "Europe in the Postwar Period," typescript, undated (Box-folder 13: 1)
    Includes related correspondence and galley proofs of the article to be published in the April 1955 issue of the American Archivist.
  - "European Unity - Dream or Possibility," holograph outline for a speech, undated (Box-folder 13: 2)
  - "Fusion and Confusion," typescript outline, undated (Box-folder 13: 3)
  - "General Development in the National and World Security Picture in the Past Five Years," holograph outline, undated (Box-folder 13: 4)
  - "Germany and Hitler," typescript speech with holograph notes, undated (Box-folder 13: 5)
  - "Germany: From Defeat to Armed Partition," typescript, undated (Box-folder 13: 6)
  - "Growth and Activity of the U.N.," holograph outline, undated (Box-folder 13: 7)
  - "Guidelines to Effective Educational Assistance in Asia," typescript speech, undated (Box-folder 13: 8)
  - "How United States Foreign Policy Is Made and Carried Out," typescript outline, undated (Box-folder 13: 9)
  - "Impact of Revolution on International Relations and the Conduct of Foreign Policy," holograph and typescript outline, undated (Box-folder 13: 10)
  - "Infiltration and Purging: The Communist Take-over of Satellite Armies," Chapter II, typescript, undated (Box-folder 13: 11)
  - "International Exchange Programs," holograph outline, undated (Box-folder 13: 12)
  - "International Organization and World Politics," typescript and printed copy, undated (Box-folder 13: 13)
  - "International Politics in Germany 1918-1933," typescript, undated (Box-folder 13: 14)
  - "International Relations in a World of Revolutionary Change," report, typescript and printed copy, undated (Box-folder 13: 15)
  - Lecture notes on European history, holograph and typescript outline, undated (Box-folder 13: 16)
  - "Legislation for Peace and Well Being," typescript, undated (Box-folder 13: 17)
  - "Lines of Force or Forces at Work," holograph, undated (Box-folder 13: 18)
  - "Long Range Policy for U.S.," typescript outline, undated (Box-folder 13: 19)
  - "Martin, Percy Alvin - An Appreciation," remarks made by Charles Rothwell and others, typescript, undated (Box-folder 13: 20)
  - "Military Integration of Europe," typescript outline for a speech, undated (Box-folder 13: 21)
  - Modern European history topics I-V, holograph and typescript notes, undated (Box-folder 13: 22)
  - Notes, holograph outline, undated (Box-folder 13: 23)
  - Notes on modern European history, holograph and typescript, undated (Box-folder 13: 24)
  - Notes on Poland, holograph outline, undated (Box-folder 13: 25)
  - "Peace Treaties Book," holograph and typescript, undated (Box-folder 13: 26)
    Includes related correspondence, 1947 August-December.
  - "Power and Peace in Asia - The Pacific Rim in Two Crucial Decades: 1960-1980," typescript, undated (Box-folder 14: 1)
    Includes a fully edited manuscript, a letter to Virginia Rothwell from the publisher, and Charles Rothwell's handwritten outline.
  - President's speech, typescript, undated (Box-folder 14: 2)
  - "Recent Trends in Europe," holograph and typescript outline, undated (Box-folder 14: 3)
    Includes assignment sheets.
  - Remarks to seniors, typescript, undated (Box-folder 14: 4)
  - Speech, City Club, typescript, undated (Box-folder 14: 5)
  - Speech delivered by Charles Easton Rothwell? on Henry Grady, typescript, undated (Box-folder 14: 6)
  - Speech on U.N.?, holograph outline, undated (Box-folder 14: 7)
  - Speech outlines, typescript, undated (Box-folder 14: 8)
  - Statement on Harold Fisher, typescript, undated (Box-folder 14: 9)
  - "Sword and Shield in Our Power Structure," typescript, undated (Box-folder 14: 10)
  - "The Changing Face of Europe," typescript, undated (Box-folder 14: 11)
  - "The Changing Map of Europe," typescript, undated (Box-folder 14: 12)
  - "The Charter of the International Trade Organization and the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade," Chapters II-V?, typescript, undated (Box-folder 14: 13)
  - "The College and World Affairs," a report of the Committee on the College and World Affairs, printed copy, undated (Box-folder 14: 14)
  - "The Conduct of Foreign Relations," holograph outline for a speech?, undated (Box-folder 15: 1)
  - "The Development of the Concepts and Practices of Peace Maintenance," typescript, undated (Box-folder 15: 2)
    Includes holograph notes by Charles Rothwell?
  - "The Genesis of the 1916 Irish Rebellion: A Study of Causes and of the Responsibility of the British and Irish Governments," typescript, undated (Box-folder 15: 3)
  - "The Great Powers," holograph outline with some typescript notes, undated (Box-folder 15: 4)
  - "The House of Morgan," typescript, undated (Box-folder 15: 5)
  - "The Inner Education," typescript remarks, undated (Box-folder 15: 6)
  - "The International Role of the American College," typescript, undated (Box-folder 15: 7)
  - "The Liberal Arts College in Higher Education," typescript, undated (Box-folder 15: 8)
  - "The Making of American Foreign Policy," holograph outline, undated (Box-folder 15: 9)
  - "The North Atlantic Alliance and the United Nations," typescript, undated (Box-folder 15: 10)
  - "The North Atlantic Pact - Are We on the Right Road and Where Does It Lead?," holograph and typescript outline, undated (Box-folder 15: 11)
    Includes brochures, clippings, memoranda, newsletter, printed matter and statements.
  - "The Primitive State of Our Foreign Relations," holograph outline for a speech?, undated (Box-folder 15: 12)
  - "The Strides of ASEAN," Chapter VIII, typescript, undated (Box-folder 15: 13)
  - "The Treaties with Italy and the German Satellites," Chapters III, IV, V and VII, jointly written by Charles Easton Rothwell and ? Dolbey, undated (Box-folder 15: 14)
    Includes related correspondence and typescript outline.
  - "The United Nations and the World Crisis," typescript outline for a speech?, undated (Box-folder 15: 15)
  - "The World in Higher Education," holograph outline, undated (Box-folder 15: 16)
  - "The World of Academia," holograph outline for a speech?, undated (Box-folder 15: 17)
  - "U.S. Representation in U.N.," holograph outline, undated (Box-folder 15: 18)
  - "U.N. and Soviet Union," Chapter V, Part II, typescript, undated (Box-folder 15: 19)
  - "War and Economy in the Twentieth Century," typescript, undated (Box-folder 16: 1)
  - "What Can Be Done?," typescript, undated (Box-folder 16: 2)
  - "World Health and World Politics," article written jointly by Charles Easton Rothwell and C. E. Allen, typescript, undated (Box-folder 16: 3)
  - "The Emergence of the Modern State," typescript outline and draft for a speech, 1939 February 21 (Box-folder 16: 4)
  - "Darwin and Revolution," holograph outline, 1941 February 11 (Box-folder 16: 5)
  - Report of the West Indian Conference, Anglo-American Caribbean Commission, Barbados, printed copy, 1944 March 21-30 (Box-folder 16: 6)
    Charles Rothwell was one of the advisers representing the United States.
  - Speech, the organization of the United Nations Conference, International Center, High School Commerce Auditorium, typescript, 1945 May 1 (Box-folder 16: 7)
  - Address, International Secretariat, typescript, 1945 May 25 (Box-folder 16: 8)
  - International Federalist Congress, article, typescript, 1946 October 14-16 (Box-folder 16: 9)
  - "United States Foreign Policy," typescript draft and outline, 1946 October 17-24 (Box-folder 16: 10)
  - "Foreign Policy Objectives of the Great Powers," preliminary typescript outline, 1946 November 29 (Box-folder 16: 11)
  - "Russia, the United States, and the Veto," KPO broadcast, typescript, 1947 October 10 (Box-folder 16: 12)
  - Motion Picture Project, typescript outline and drafts, 1947 October - 1949 January (Box-folder 16: 13)
    Includes related correspondence and minutes of meetings.
  - "Which Path Towards World Government?," summary for World Affairs Broadcast, San Francisco News, San Francisco, California, typescript, 1947 October 24 (Box-folder 16: 14)
  - "The United Nations and the World Crisis," speech, Santa Cruz, California, holograph outline, 1948 April 9 (Box-folder 16: 15)
  - "This Is Our World," speech, Forty Ninth Annual Convention, California Congress of Parents and Teachers, Sacramento, California, typescript, 1948 May 12 (Box-folder 17: 1)
    Includes related correspondence.
  - "1948 - Year of Decision," introductory remarks, General Session, Stanford Alumni Conference, Stanford University, California, typescript, 1948 May 15 (Box-folder 17: 2)
    Includes related correspondence, memoranda, and program.
  - "An American View of the World in 1948," commencement address, San Francisco State College, holograph and typescript outline, 1948 June 15 (Box-folder 17: 3)
  - "The Prospects for the United Nations," typescript, 1948 July 20 (Box-folder 17: 4)
  - "The United Nations and the World Crisis," lecture, World Affairs Council of Northern California, Watsonville High School, Watsonville, California, typescript outline, 1948 October 21 (Box-folder 17: 5)
  - "World Affairs Are Your Affairs," World Affairs Broadcast, San Francisco News, San Francisco, California, tentative holograph and typescript outline, 1948 October 22 (Box-folder 17: 6)
  - Speech, UNESCO Contributions to World Peace, California English Teachers' Association, holograph outline, 1948 November 6 (Box-folder 17: 7)
  - "World Affairs Are Your Affairs," broadcast on Bernadotte Report for Palestine, tentative typescript outline, 1948 November 12 (Box-folder 17: 8)
  - "International Relations in a World of Revolutionary Change," revised from an article in World Politics, typescript and printed copy, 1949 January (Box-folder 17: 9)
  - "The United Nations in a World of Crisis," speech, Bakersfield Forum, Institute of World Affairs, Harvey Auditorium, Bakersfield High School and College, California, typescript outline, 1949 March 3 (Box-folder 17: 10)
    Includes related correspondence and schedule.
  - "Trusteeship System," speech, Monterey, California, holograph and typescript outline, 1949 March 10 (Box-folder 17: 11)
  - ""Films for World-Minded American Citizenship," typescript, 1949 March 17 (Box-folder 17: 12)
  - "The Democratic Challenge to Totalitarianism," Salinas, California, typescript outline for a speech, 1949 September 21 (Box-folder 17: 13)
  - "Is the U.N. Getting Anywhere?," holograph outline for a speech, 1949 October 17 (Box-folder 17: 14)
  - "Sticks or Bricks and a Peaceful World," holograph and typescript outline and draft, 1949 October 28 (Box-folder 17: 15)
  - Broadcast, clippings only, 1949 November 21-26 (Box-folder 17: 16)
  - Remarks for Harold Fisher, typescript, 1949 November 27 (Box-folder 17: 17)
  - "Education, Citizenship and Peace," speech, Teachers' Institute, typescript outline, 1949 December 16 (Box-folder 17: 18)
  - "Germany: From Defeat to Armed Partition," typescript material to be used in Course VI at the National War College (1951 October 29-November 9), 1951 October 24 (Box-folder 17: 19)
  - "Great Power Relationships," speech, International Affairs Unit, Navy Reserve Officers' group, typescript outline, 1951 November 12 (Box-folder 17: 20)
  - "How Can Europe Become Strong?," speech, Stanford University and Los Angeles Alumni Conference, typescript, 1952 January-March (Box-folder 17: 21)
  - "The Problem of Formulating American Foreign Policy," typescript, 1952 February (Box-folder 17: 22)
  - "The Continuing Crisis in International Relations," speech, Regional Conference on Universities and World Affairs, Reed College, Portland, Oregon, holograph and typescript outline, 1952 February 22-24 (Box-folder 17: 23)
    Includes related correspondence, statement of expenses, and telegram.
  - "Trouble Spots of the World," typescript remarks for a television show, 1952 March (Box-folder 17: 24)
  - "The Prospects for Europe," lecture series, U.S. Naval Postgraduate School, Monterey, California, typescript outline, 1952 June 20 (Box-folder 17: 25)
  - "An Explanation of the Hoover Institute and Library," speech prepared for the Alumni Conference, Salt Lake City, Utah, typescript, 1953 February 5 (Box-folder 17: 26)
  - "The United Nations and United States National Security," American Friends Service Conference, San Diego, typescript outline, 1953 March 7 (Box-folder 17: 27)
  - "We the Peoples of the United Nations...," speech, 30th Annual Conference, National Association College Unions, University of California, Berkeley, California, holograph outline and typescript text, 1953 April 15 (Box-folder 17: 28)
  - "International Organization and World Politics," Columbia University Topical Studies in International Relations Program, typescript outline for a book?, 1953 July 24 (Box-folder 17: 29)
  - "Resources and Research in the Hoover Institute and Library," paper, Annual Meeting, American Historical Association, Chicago, printed copy and typescript, 1953 December 29 (Box-folder 17: 30)
  - "If the Hoover Tower Could Speak," excerpts from address, Stanford Conference, Salt Lake City, Utah and Denver, Colorado, typescript, 1954 February 6-7 (Box-folder 17: 31)
    Includes program.
  - "Perspectives on the United Nations," holograph and typescript notes on Western Civilization, 1954 May 31 (Box-folder 17: 32)
  - "Post-War Trends in American Economy," holograph outline, 1954 July 1 (Box-folder 17: 33)
  - "The Hoover Institute and Library," remarks, Dean's luncheon, Stanford University, holograph notes and typescript outline, 1955 January 11 (Box-folder 17: 34)
  - "The Price of a Free World," speech, Western College Conference on American Foreign Policy, Institute of International Relations, Stanford University, typescript, 1955 January 30-February 2 (Box-folder 17: 35)
    Includes bibliography, clippings, holograph notes, and tentative agenda.
  - "Through the Lion's Eyes: The British Look at U.S. and Our Policies," remarks, Stanford Alumni Conference, Monterey, California, typescript, 1955 March 5 (Box-folder 18: 1)
    Includes clippings and correspondence.
  - "The United States and the United Nations," holograph outline, 1955 March 8 (Box-folder 18: 2)
    Includes other holograph and typescript outlines for speeches on the United Nations.
  - "Benchmarks in the Atomic Era," speech, Commonwealth Dinner Club, Los Angeles, California, typescripts, 1955 March 24 (Box-folder 18: 3)
    Includes clippings and holograph notes.
  - "Resources and Records in the Hoover Institute and Library," reprint from the American Archivist, 1955 April (Box-folder 18: 4)
  - "New Horizons of Interdependence," speech, Program on Overseas Development, Stanford University, California, typescript, 1955 July 22 (Box-folder 18: 5)
  - "A New Europe in a New World," Stanford School of Business Conference, Stanford University, California, typescript outline for a speech, 1955 July 25 (Box-folder 18: 6)
    Includes related correspondence and program.
  - "New Horizons of Interdependence," speech, Program of Overseas Development, Stanford University, California, typescript, 1955 August 26 (Box-folder 18: 7)